three sections and we see those laid out
in exodus exodus 27 verse 9 says
i shall make the court of the tabernacle
for the south side
southward there shall be hangings for
the court of fine twined linen
of a hundred cubits long for one side so
it's talking about what we see here this
white
um this white basically like a wall
right
the fine-tined linen and so that is the
court the outer court and then exodus 26
33 um explains to us the other two
sections which are it says thou shalt
hang up the veil
under the tashes that thou may bring in
thither within the veil the ark of the
testimony
and the veil shall divide unto you
between
the holy place and the most holy place
so here we see three sections we see the
courtyard also known as the outer court
then we see the holy place and the most
holy place
and so what we're going to do is break
down each one of these three
uh sections because each of them has its
own significance
and it has its own uh furniture that
goes along with it
so what's found then in the outer court
exodus 29
11 says thou shalt kill the bullock
before the lord
by the door of the tabernacle
of the congregation so the tabernacle of
the congregation is the sanctuary
by the door of the sanctuary you will
kill a bullock
and verse 12 says thou shalt take the
blood of the bullock
and put it upon the horns of the altar
with thy finger and pour all the blood
beside the bottom of the altar so
they're sacrificing
on this altar verse 18 says
uh so verses 12 through 18 are
describing in detail what they're
supposed to do with the sacrifice that
is made
so you can go back and read those but i
just wanted to highlight
what the furniture was and so that first
piece of furniture once again
is the altar of sacrifice verse 18 says
and thou shalt burn the whole ram upon
the altar
it is a burnt offering unto the lord it
is a sweet savor
an offering made by fire unto the lord
so again this is where
the sacrifice is made
so one thing also that i'd like to point
out is that the
um altar was made it was overlaid with
brass it says exodus 27
1 thou shall make an altar of wood five
cubits long five cubits broad
and they also shall be four square and
the height thereof shall be three cubits
and thou shall make the horns of it upon
the four corners thereof
his horn shall be the same and thou
shalt overlay it with brass that's going
to be important
an important distinction later so here
in the image you see
by the door of the con of the tabernacle
of the congregation
the first thing is for them to make a
sacrifice
now what does this sacrifice represent i
know my christian brothers and sisters
we already know
john 1 1 29 uh he john the baptist saw
jesus coming toward him
and said behold the lamb of god who
takes away the sins
of the world the sin of the world so
this
this portion this first piece of
furniture is a reference to a symbolic
representation of the sacrifice
that christ was coming to make and so
once again we've kind of touched on this
throughout the series
and that is the lord has given this
entire ceremonial system
the sanctuary the tabernacle all of the
items in it
he has given these things as a plan a a
a blueprint as pastor myers likes to
call it
to for us to be able to understand and
for the jews back then to have been able
to understand
what it was god was planning to do to
save them
and so the first thing they would have
known is that there was going to be a
sacrifice
made for their sins um in one of these
verses i believe it was exodus 27 and
when you read the in between the the
verses that i did not read
it talks about how aaron had to lay his
hands and his sons were to lay their
hands
on the um animal that was to be
sacrificed and confess the sins of the
people
over that animal so the animal was
sacrificed
in as a shadow as a type of what christ
was coming to do our sins laid upon him
and he died for us so then what else is
found in the art of court we saw this
here
the altar of sacrifice there is another
item before we move
to the inward structure which contains
the other two compartments
and so the next thing is uh exodus
chapter 30
verse 18 thou shalt make a laver of
brass
and his foot also of grass to wash with
and thou shalt put it between
the tabernacle of the congregation and
the altar and thou shalt put water there
in for aaron and his sons to wash their
hands and their feet
there when they go into the tabernacle
of the congregation
they shall wash with water so that they
don't die or when they come near
the altar to minister uh to burn
offering made by fire unto the lord
so if the first altar represents
sacrifice
what can we find is going to be the
anti-type or the thing that was
pointing to in the new testament we see
in acts
2 verse 38 peter said unto them repent
and be baptized every one of you in the
name of jesus christ for the remission
of sins
and you shall receive the gift of the
holy ghost
so it represents baptism but then what
does
baptism take it a step further what does
baptism
represent the answer is in romans 6
3 know ye not that as many of us were
baptized were baptized into jesus christ
we're baptized
into his death so there are many things
that
that the labor represents that water
represents
uh the bible talks about not being
conformed to the world but being
transformed by the renewing of our minds
it talks about having been cleansed of
sin
and washed our filth being washed away
um there are many things that this water
represents
uh but as it relates specifically to
christ's mission
we see the altar of sacrifice and then
the next thing we see also
refers to that act of his death we are
baptized into his death and we get up as
we know
out of the water with newness of life
now notice also
that the laver was also called a laver
of brass so i told you that we would
come back to that
so the articles on the outside of the
of well it's kind of it's the outside
it's the outer court the the articles in
the outer court
were both constructed with gr with brass
right and then we'll see
what metal was used for the articles
that are
inside inside the structure we can't see
inside right now
um in this image um also something that
we should take note of
and something i think is really
important and and that is
this represents like i said christ's
mission it
it talks about what he came to do so for
the first
30 years of christ's life he would have
been
symbolically dwelling amongst the people
and we see the people
um living around surrounding the
sanctuary surrounding the tabernacle
christ came to dwell among men this is
what the bible says right
and then so he moves into he moves
into the outer court and his life is
offered as a sacrifice in his death
for us and so again the theme of
tonight's study is
the investigative judgment jesus and the
scapegoat well we're talking about
so many things here there's so much
there's so much to be
um to be pulled out of these things that
god has laid down for us to understand
right
but i just want you guys to see one
prominent theme here is that
the scripture all of the prophecies all
of the
the ceremonial uh types all of these
things point to christ and his mission
and so in his life and his mission we
should see a parallel from the new
testament there should always be a
corresponding parallel
from the old testament because
everything in the new testament builds
upon
the foundation that was already laid by
god in the old testament
so once again these are the things that
we saw so far
and now we can't see what's inside the
sanctuary just yet
but i'm going to hand the floor over to
evangelist lemon and he is going to
explain to us what is inside of that
first compartment
inside of the tabernacle